William Liu

☐ (608) 886-3074 // @ me@williamliu.me // ☐ www.williamliu.me

Bio

I am a software engineer, as well as a computer scientist and cognitive scientist.

I generally find myself working on problems in parallel systems/algorithms, domain-specific compilers, human-Al interaction, deep learning, linguistics, and applications of cognitive science.

I usually work on developing robust large-scale systems, and also doing applied research.

For a shorter overview of my work, please check out my resume at: williamliu.me/Rez_U_May.pdf

Updated: Jan 30, 2022

Education

The University of Texas at Austin // Austin, Texas

Master of Science in Computer Science (Part Time, Remote)

Dec 2023 (Expected)

Carnegie Mellon University // Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania

Bachelor of Science in Cognitive Science

Minor in Computer Science

Alpha Epsilon Pi Fraternity

Research Advisor: Saugata Ghose

University of Wisconsin—Madison // Madison, Wisconsin

High School Dual Enrollment in Applied Mathematics, Engineering and Physics (AMEP)

May 2016

May 2020

Professional Experience

CoPilot // Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (Remote)

Backend Systems Engineer

- Build, manage, and maintain the entire backend infrastructure of the company
- Design systems for coaches to communicate with clients about exercise movements
- Create data pipelines and perform data analysis for key business metrics

SambaNova Systems // Palo Alto, California

Software Engineer

Jun 2020 — Aug 2021

Aug 2021 - Present

- Led small team to increase performance of multiple 2D and 3D computer-vision ML models more than 10X on custom hardware
- Designed and optimized architecture-specific high-throughput convolution operators
- Built optimizing compiler for ML and high-performance computing applications, and designed and implemented dataflow graph optimizations algorithms in the compiler

Nvidia // Santa Clara, California

Deep Learning Software Intern

May 2019 - Aug 2019

- Machine learning model compression for custom embedded processor
- Designed and built new performance testing infrastructure for all embedded ML apps

Uber // Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania

Software Engineering Intern

May 2018 — Aug 2018

- Surveyed, designed, and implemented multiple latency reduction algorithms in the autonomous vehicle distributed operating system's message-passing protocol

Skills

Programming Languages:

Python, TypeScript, JavaScript, C, C++, SML, MATLAB, Octave, R, OCaml

Machine Learning:

PyTorch, Tensorflow, Keras, High-Resolution Image Processing, Semantic Segmentation

Web Development:

GraphQL, React, PostgreSQL, NextJS, Urql, TypeORM, AWS, DigitalOcean, Vercel, Fastify, Express, MongoDB, Flask

Tools:

LLVM, Cuda, OpenMP, Open MPI, Unix, Git, Perforce

Design:

InDesign, Photoshop, Illustrator, Adobe XD, Sketch, AutoCAD, SolidWorks, Figma, User Research

Languages:

Mandarin Chinese (Basic Professional Proficiency), Japanese (Very Basic)

Miscellaneous:

LaTeX, Gantt Charts, Agile Software Development, Asana, JIRA

Research Experience

The University of Texas at Austin // Austin, Texas

Graduate Researcher Jan 2022 - Present

Research Areas: Augmented Reality, Asynchronous Collaboration, Human-Al

Interaction, Physical-Digital Information Representation

Research Advisor: Amy Pavel

Computer Architecture Lab at Carnegie Mellon // Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania

Research Assistant Dec 2016 – May 2020

Research Areas: Operating Systems and Memory Architecture

Research Advisor: Saugata Ghose

CMU Articulab // Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania

Research Intern Aug 2017 — Dec 2017

Research Areas: Rapport Modeling and Human-Al Interaction **Research Advisors:** Michael Madaio and Justine Cassell

Scientific Publications

M. Emani, V. Vishwanath, C. Adams, M. E. Papka, R. Stevens, L. Florescu, S. Jairath, W. Liu, T. Nama, and A. Sujeeth "Accelerating Scientific Applications With SambaNova Reconfigurable Dataflow Architecture" in Computing in Science & Engineering, Vol. 23, No. 2, pp. 114-119, Mar 2021

S Ghose, A G Yağlıkçı, R Gupta, D Lee, K Kudrolli, **W X. Liu**, H Hassan, K K. Chang, N Chatterjee, A Agrawal, M O'Connor, O Mutlu

"What Your DRAM Power Models Are Not Telling You: Lessons from a Detailed Experimental Study"

in Proc. of the ACM SIGMETRICS Conference, Irvine, CA, June 2018

in Proc. of the ACM on Measurement and Analysis of Computing Systems (POMACS), Vol. 2, No. 3, Dec 2018

Teaching Experience

15-418 Parallel Computer Architecture and Programming // Carnegie Mellon University **Teaching Assistant** (Rating: 5.0/5)

Spring 2020

- 15-418 "provides a deep understanding of the fundamental principles and engineering trade-offs involved in designing modern parallel computing systems as well as teaches parallel programming techniques necessary to effectively utilize these machines"
- Designed homework/exam questions, held office hours, answered questions on Piazza

85-310 Research Methods in Cognitive Psychology // Carnegie Mellon University **Head Teaching Assistant** (Rating: 4.5/5)

Spring 2020

- 85-310 teaches students how to conduct independent research in cognitive science by designing, running, and evaluating a novel research project and writing up a report
- Graded reports, designed guizzes, provided supplemental lectures, held office hours

15-110 Principles of Computing // Carnegie Mellon University

Teaching Assistant (Rating: 4.8/5) Fall 2019 **Teaching Assistant** (Rating: 5.0/5) Fall 2018 **Teaching Assistant** (Rating: 4.6/5) Spring 2018 Fall 2017 **Teaching Assistant** (Rating: 3.5/5)

- 15-110 is a fast-paced and broad introduction to the field of computer science that introduces basic theory and programming techniques
- Lectured recitation sessions, graded homework and exams, held office hours

Projects Detailed descriptions for all projects can be found at: https://williamliu.me/categories/project/

Ice Hockey Agent // Course Project, Dec 2021

Designed and implemented an agent that plays ice hockey in a MarioKart-esque game environment. Used PyTorch to design a fully-convolutional model for detecting game features and reinforcement learning to act.

Reducing Cache Pollution at Compile Time // Course Project, May 2020

Reduced cache pollution in large memory streaming applications by inserting non-temporal memory instructions through multiple compiler passes

Improving CNN Interpretability // Course Project, May 2019

Improve CNN kernel interpretability by guiding and extracting kernel gradient convergence results using parttemplates which can be used to interpret model convergence behavior

Parallel Galaxy Simulation // Course Project, May 2019

Built and optimized parallel galaxy simulator with a lock-free quadtree and experimented with different parallel numerical integration methods

Simon // PennApps XVIII Hackathon, Sep 2018

Train a robot to do a simple mechanical task by doing it yourself and the robot will mimic your actions Top 30 Hack

Modware // PennApps XVII Hackathon, Jan 2018

Grand Prize out of 14 finalists from 11 different countries

Prototype with basic modular hardware components by controlling the "wiring" through software 2nd Place Overall, Best Hardware Hack, Hacker's Choice Award, and Best IoT Prize

Facebook Discourse // Facebook Global Hackathon Finals, Nov 2017 Digitize and organize political debates in real time to streamline political media ResistAR // TartanHacks 2017 Hackathon, Feb 2017

Augmented reality app that visualizes the voltage across and current through each component in a circuit **Grand Prize**

Autonomous Ground Support Equipment // NASA's Centennial Challenge, Apr 2016

Autonomous robotics system to support a rocket launch carrying payload

2nd Place as the only high school team in this college competition

Select Coursework

Mathematics and CS Theory:

Neural Network Design, Topics in Deep Learning, Topology and Modal Logic, Parallel Algorithms, Functional Programming, Machine Learning, Computational Perception, Numerical Analysis and Algebra, Theoretical Computer Science

Systems:

Optimizing Compilers, Parallel Computer Architecture, Advanced Operating Systems

Psychology:

Consciousness, Adaptive Neural Decision Making, Systems Neuroscience, Human Factors in Design, Neural Foundations of Behavior

Organization Involvement

CMU Tricking Club	I highly encourage you to look up Tricking if you like gymnastics or parkour :)
-------------------	---

Member	Jan 2020 — May 2020
Co-Founder and President	Dec 2016 — Jan 2020

Cognitive Science Student Advisory Board

Treasurer	Aug 2018 – May 2020
Board Member	Jan 2018 — Aug 2018

Scotch'n'Soda Theatre

Assistant Director for RENT	Feb 2020 — Mar 2020
Production Manager for The House of Yes	Jan 2018 — Feb 2018
Stage Manager for Young Frankenstein	Aug 2017 - Oct 2017
Stage Manager for Heathers: The Musical	Feb 2017 — Apr 2017
Assistant Stage Manager for Rosencrantz and Guildenstern are Dead	Jan 2017 — Feb 2017
Hair and Makeup Artist for <i>Murder Ballad</i>	Sep 2016 - Oct 2016

St. Mary's Hospital

Inpatient Volunteer	Jul 2013 — May 2015
---------------------	---------------------

Professional Affiliations

IEEE, IEEE TCuARCH, IEEE TCCA, ACM, ACM SIGARCH

Interests

Anime/Animation, Photography, Music, Writing, Weight Lifting, League of Legends, Filmmaking, Pokémon